data structures and algorithms we get
this question all the time I actually
made another video about this the video
was specifically about Elite code Elite
code
interviews um you know obsessing about
being able to do yeah Elite code skills
and all of that and I got another
question though today and it kind of It
kind of um got me to thinking that
because this the question was
specifically about
um algorithms and data structures and
the question I think was something like
what do you think about data structures
and algorithms and that is a separate
question from how much time should you
spend on preparing for lead code
interviews right that I have a video
about that and I think it's important
that I make this video because I don't
want anybody to
misunderstand I think mastering
algorithms and data structures
uh is a huge part of any programming
skill set you should eventually do it
and let me I'm actually going to site
from a book here that we are going that
I'm going to be recommending to you um
this is Kyle ludal from mastering
algorithms in C my favorite book which
I'll talk about more in a bit and he
says here at the bottom after talking
about this pegboard game that he used to
play with his I think his sister um he
says often people deal with information
in in Fairly loose forms such as pegs on
a board notes in a notebook or drawings
in a portfolio however to process
information with a computer the
information needs to be more formally
organized in addition it is helpful to
have a precise plan for exactly what to
do with the information data structures
and algorithms help us with this simply
stated they help us develop programs
that are in a word elegant as developers
of software it is important to remember
that we must be more than just
proficient with programming languages
and development tools developing
software is a matter of craftsmanship a
good understanding of data structures
and algorithms is important to becoming
part and of becoming such a Craftsman um
and I regularly refer to programming as
an art form it's not really I'm married
to an artist and but craftsmanship yes
right and if you want to take your
coding to the next level you kind of
need to understand how to organize that
information does that mean you need to
memorize a bunch of stuff and be able to
perform leak interviews faster than
anybody else I don't think so I do think
it does mean that you should understand
as many forms of organizing data as
possible and and traversing the data and
a lot of people would argue that's the
same thing as lead code I don't I don't
agree I I do think that some of the
algorithms and and the ways of thinking
are encouraged through lead code but um
I think it's I think that the general
idea of of knowing how to you know
structure a problem and then come at it
is is is a big part of that um you know
I I did CS 101 actually the prim agan
recently did a video about Pascal who
was reviewing a doc an older document
and I was lapping during the whole thing
because I actually was uh forced to
learn Pascal and CS 101 uh before I
changed my major to Russian and I just
remember the distinction between a
function and a pro and a procedure which
if you don't know the distinction can
can get you into trouble and that that's
not necessarily an algor or a data
structure but it is a bit of information
that that could help you and you'll have
to watch another video to understand the
difference between the two if you don't
know but it it's kind of in line with
this idea that data structures and
algorithms uh make you a better
programmer right um and So eventually
you should have them it doesn't mean
that you need to add them right now and
use them to get past you know the the
gatekeeping interview that's keeping you
out of the software engineering job that
you want unless you're going for a very
highlevel um software engineering I
don't like that term at all I have
another video on that you know if you're
going for that kind of thing then yeah
you should really be able to build every
single data structure from scratch and
maybe if that's your thing but I would
suggest that that is not necessary for
most people and that's why I don't talk
about this stuff I don't have this
required in the Boost this is an extra
video that talks about what I think
about algorithms specifically and data
so algorithms data structures are things
so okay so having said all that they do
have value so how do you go about
learning them what's the best way and as
with everything I have lots of videos on
this I think the best way to learn it is
to build something that you need that
uses it now this this gets this gets you
know sometimes you might need to have
some sort of you know memorable mini
project uh that just does the one thing
that you need to learn like link list or
something um but there's a good chance
you're not going to remember it as well
if you do that in fact um when I was the
way that I got into rooted node trees uh
wasn't until you know several years
recently uh that I got into it because I
wanted to make I wanted to make my own
parsing language I wanted to
transpile um uh markdown into something
else and in order to do that I had to
understand what a node tree was and how
every one of those words constitutes you
know essentially a node in the list and
and how do you go through them all then
I I had I had a very immediate need to
do that I wanted to be able to to
process all that and it turns out that
that that that personal desire to figure
out how to do that um informed later um
the work that was a work requirement to
Traverse all of the data points in a
yamel tree in a way that would reliably
and I made videos about this um that
would reliably change the key value pair
such as like every for for every key
that of tag no matter where it is in the
entire tree change its value to this say
for example you want to change uh from
docker.io to your own internal you know
Harbor um changing the value of of all
of the tags including you know that was
a very real world need and it required
that I Traverse uh the rooted no tree
and I was able to do that because I had
spent time trying to learn how to do
rooted no trees in my in my in the thing
for pegan so I'm still before I get into
like how I think you should learn it I
do think that the best way is for you to
find something you want to do and and
that might be hard right because does
anybody really want to make a linked
list why would you care about that right
um well you you you'll care when you're
starting to deal with data and you need
to be able to manipulate the data um and
that doesn't really happen until you
have data to manipulate in some way and
a lot of a lot of people that are just
starting out won't have that need yet
and by the way I don't think you need to
learn this stuff up front but it when
when it comes time to learn it where
should you go learn it um so there's
there's two two main places to learn it
and I'm just going to say the one of
them is it's the blue book I forget the
name of it I'm not even going to mention
it because I don't think you should go
there and pay it's like
$170 it's this extremely
dense um overpriced piece of crap that
is the standard book that everybody has
to buy for computer science um I bought
it because I wanted to review it I mean
the thing is like seriously thick you
could kill somebody with it and and I
did study some of the maybe like 10
pages of it for rooted node trees which
turned out that I could have understood
any of that just by going to the
internet and and paid a lot less money
and not have been as you know confused
by it the writing is horrible so so I am
going to mention that though because a
lot of who go through computer science
um are going to be forced to buy that
book so I wanted to just briefly say
what I thought about that but more
importantly uh I think the book that
that I I really want to to um to kind of
mention is algorithms with C from Kyle
ludal so that that statement I made
about that statement that I read about
using algorithms with C uh comes from
from Kyle and why do I recommend this
book above all the other ones given how
old it is okay so this thing was
released in
1999 but there are a number of reasons
that it's okay for a book on algorithms
to be old because algorithms and data
structures I'm going to get roasted for
saying this but they largely haven't
changed since the beginning right they
are largely the same things and um for
that reason I think the the the
selection criteria for where you're
going to learn this from becomes more a
matter of learning style and and
mentorship and and voice and examples
and projects and things like that and on
every one of those counts I put Kyle
loudon's book above everything else and
I just really encourage you to get it
it's it's you can actually get it for
free these days as a PDF um it there
there are a number of books out there if
anybody else has other things want to
recommend this is fine put it in the
comments you can you're welcome to do
that but but I want to talk to you about
my favorite my favorite book about
algorithms and why I think this is still
the best book um the number one reason
that I like Kyle's book is because it's
simple to process in fact he talks about
this in the beginning um uh here it
actually says it right here using a
programming style and writing style that
are exceptionally clean Kyle Lon shows
you how to use such a essential data
list structures as lists Stacks cues
sets trees heaps priority cues and
graphs these are the basics right these
are I mean these are just hands down
they're the basics uh it explains how to
use algorithms for sorting searching
numerical analysis data compression data
encryption common graph problems
computational geometry and I mean these
these These are the fundamentals my
friends these These are these are the
things that if you're if you want to say
that you have a a handle on algorithms
which these days kind of implies data
structures um that you know and I kind
of do wish they would start with
algorithms that's actually one of the
reasons I like it it's mastering
algorithms with C well the algorithms
imply a data structure of some kind uh
people you always refer to it as data
structures and algorithms it would
actually made it harder for me to find
the book again um because that's not how
he sees it he deserves the relative
efficiency of all Implement he describes
the relative efficiency of all of these
implementations the compression
encryption chapters not only give you
working code for reasonable efficient
solutions they offer explanations of
concept and approachable manner for
people who have never had the time or
expertise to study them in depth and
this I really want to punch this point
when you learn about Kyle when you learn
about his life his life has I think he
was a a an airline traffic controller um
his life has been dedicated dedicated to
solving problems he his brain is
designed to create actual solutions for
real problems and so his entire writing
style and his entire approach is 100%
practical he's like okay here's the
problem and here's what this is going to
get us this is why it matters and that
is why Kyle is my favorite author on
this topic there are lots of other
people um who have talked about these
kind of things it is a 25y old book it
is but we're talking about you know sets
Stacks heaps priority cues graphs these
are Tech these are things that haven't
changed in 20 computer the the data
structure and algorithm theory has
largely remained unchanged for 25 years
thank God right now the the more um I
suppose liberal use of memory such as
was defined by the parsing expression
grammar you know Peg which I of course
extended with my pegan notation um you
know these kind of ideas hey we have
memory now we can use infinite look
ahead instead of single automat right th
those algorithms have changed in fact
the Dragon book is largely Irrelevant in
2024 even though it's still taught in
schools um because many of the concepts
from it don't apply in a world we have a
limited memory but to be fair when we're
talking about data structures and
algorithms um we're still talking about
Concepts that have remained the same why
see another another big criticism of
this book that I'm going to get in the
comments is why on Earth would I learn
data structures and algorithms and c I
can't code those in a code interview
really quickly and this brings me back
to the reason that this video exists
versus the lead code interview the
there's the regular advice and you can
go find the same advice out there I'll
let you find it for yourself is that if
you're going to get a job at Google or
wherever that you need to pick a
language that you can write data
structures and algorithms in quickly and
cleanly and almost universally they will
we're doing a video right now so that is
now in the video I just want you to know
that so so you know keep the comments
relevant um so the point is that the
fact that it's c is actually a good
thing and let me make a case for that so
um everybody needs to understand C you
don't have to write in it every day you
don't if you want to every single
technologist needs to understand what C
is doing they need to understand whether
you're an operations person and you all
the all the system calls when you run s
Trace against the process it's all C and
and there's a separate video I'll do
about that so the fact that this
algorithms in C mastering algorithms in
C is actually a good thing because it
might be old C doesn't matter because
it's helping you understand C from the
perspective of a time when data
structures and algorithms were not
codified behind standardized libraries
and other languages like go and rust and
and modern sea and C Lang and everything
and and and all all Zig and everything
so I mean you can make the argument
really solidly today that nobody really
has to understand all the data
structures and algorithms to get a job
because most of the coding tasks are
about connecting the dots they're not
about creating elegant algorithms unless
you're you know a real real pure
software engineer most of the data most
of the coding stuff is writing apis and
plugging things together it's crud you
know create replace update delete that
kind of stuff that's that's the
day-to-day bread and butter kind of work
that has to be done with coding and
there are a lot and m i I believe from
Facebook in an really ancient video from
code.org said the very same thing most
of the common daily tasks that need to
be done in programming and high-paying
jobs even do not require a a deep level
of understanding for mastering you know
algorithms in C but if and when you do
need to learn c um one of the best ways
to learn C is to implement and to repeat
TJ Hollow chuk a very famous uh
developer you know redoing something
that's already been done to see if you
can do it better right well by anytime
you use a key value hash and go or any
other language you're using you're
you're the underlying code you're doing
you're you're using some sort of hashing
algorithm that is looking that the the
content of that key value pair up it's
every single language has implemented it
differently so understanding how go and
python or rust implement the hashing
algorithm for key value pairs in their
maps and lists or whatever they call
them it's valuable It's like because
when you say well why does it take me
longer why would I use this you know
sync map and go for example versus a
regular map because the method of
looking it up it's also you might you
might understand why originally there
was a debate about whether go Maps were
even safer concurrency because the
lookup algorithm sometimes will cash the
last most frequently you know looked up
key uh and and give it first if it
because it's the most frequent one and
that that in term that requires writing
uh temporary cache to memory in order to
to make the next queries faster that
that entire thing I just described is an
algorithm that's an algorithm that uses
a very internal data structure and how
does that data structure get implemented
so by understanding data structures and
algorithms you will understand how your
computer works better uh you'll be able
to Think Through problems at a macro
level uh much better like in terms of
like how do I deploy my infrastructure
do I use one of these data structures in
a a sort of a macro meta you know way uh
or do I you know so it does help you to
learn how to think and all that but I I
would make the argument that learning it
in C is perhaps probably the most
valuable thing you can do are do that
mean you're going to be busting C out in
your in your you know timed lead code
interview no you're not but but you'll
understand so much more if you when you
do finally decide to add you know data
structures and algorithms to your tool
set you'll understand them far better if
you do them in C because every other
language has already implemented them
you would never ever in fact I would
argue if you tried to reimplement a
rooted node tree for some reason that
doesn't exist especially now that we
have generics and go you know or to try
to reimplement a slice and go right
which is you know key it's like a whole
bunch of values in a list like in Python
you would never reimplement that you
might use that to you're you're going to
use the stuff that's already been given
to you these languages already provide
it because these languages are so high
level you know um but then but but when
you when so so if and when you're ready
to understand these things understanding
them in a language that is an extremely
lowle language anguage and imagining how
they've been implemented in these other
languages which were all originally
written in C by the way is extremely
valuable is is it going to make you
faster than the leak code interview no
it's not it's going to make you
knowledgeable it's going to give you a
really core understanding of I mean to
to just just something like pointers and
C understanding what a pointer is in C
in order to understand how to make a
linked list is extr extremely valuable
and that that understanding of a pointer
might come about because you learned how
to use pointers and go or rust uh
JavaScript doesn't have pointers of
course um but you know understanding how
to do a link list by using pointers in C
gives you C is already a language that
doesn't have these things so so the
thing that's really cool about that is
that while you're learning these really
important Concepts data structures and
algorithms you're also imagining you're
better able to imagine how they've been
implemented in these other languages
which are written in C you see how it
goes and then and then you could even
maybe write your own and make a better
version of those things right and and
see so it helps you so by doing Master
algorithms a c you're focusing on the
algorithms and the organization and what
a q is and what a tree is and all that
but first in first out and all these
Concepts and that's important that you
do understand those things a lot of you
are going to go like well no duh because
most of the data structures that exist
are really common sense for most people
right so if I you know you you already
like the idea of a q a q is just a line
so imagine a line at the at the post
office you deal with the first person
and then the next person and then you
the next person you know most most of
the stuff that exist most of these these
ideas of data structures they're not
complicated they're already things that
exist in nature all the time and you
probably if you're a logical thinker you
probably like oh that's what they call
okay I get it
right and and you're going to understand
it's going to be very intuitive so you
shouldn't be afraid of it um and neither
should you be afraid of c and and if
there's one author and I I keep going on
and on about this but if there's one
author who really makes this entire
topic totally practical and totally
approachable and downright fun lots of
stories and you know experiences from
The Real World as well as really solid
examples of how this is actually
implemented in these languages Inc this
is a great great great book for that and
it has withstood the test of time in my
opinion and it gives you a tremendous
ability to be productive right out of
the gate so so I recommend strongly that
that you go for Kyle lon's book and
we'll let the we'll let the thumbnail be
here I'm going to try to maybe I can
zoom in on this so um uh and I as I
mentioned because it is so old it it is
obviously it's it's available out there
uh for you to get in in other ways
um go watch my video about whether you
should pay for books or not um that's up
to you but I I think you should probably
consider it um I will end this video by
saying that I personally uh am not going
to do anything with algorithms see uh as
a part of the beginner boost and uh it
won't be until all the Boost is
completely done before I even consider
working through algorithms and C with
the group um but you're welcome to go do
that on your own and somebody asked is
it valuable to learn it and the answer
is yes just not first I would I I think
people and I talk about in the LOD
interview definitely put this in your
list of things that you eventually want
to master and learn but don't waste too
much time with this now especially if
you're trying to get through the
beginner boost or something like that to
get a job um I truly believe that it's
more important for you to have a body of
work of you doing things and even a lab
where you've set up systems and created
your own apis and things that are doing
things that you will like and want to
show off more than saying I've got X and
such score on lead code interview um if
you want to go that route that's totally
up to you and that's fine I just think
it for most people for most people that
that's a waste of time and that that's
all in another video but when the time
comes for you to truly understand this
stuff go with Kyle and see what you
think